Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ג׳. Gimmel.
We pick up on the bottom of עמוד ב׳ Amud Bet and
we are dealing with the question of whether יש אונס בגיטין, yesh
ones begitin, whether the claim that, whether the fact that somebody, somebody
makes a stipulation that a גט get should take place under certain
conditions, whether the fact that there was an אונס, ones, something out
of the person's control,
or some act of God or some other thing, got sick or
whatever, whether that's a factor and whether that should make us sort
of look at the situation as if what he would have done
without that אונס ones having occurred. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara first
position is אין אונס בגיטין, ein ones begitin, we do not factor
that in and as was pointed out yesterday and as we're going
to see in the גמרא, Gemara,
that obviously if we would factor that in, that would make things
very complicated because you would then never really know whether certain conditions
were met or not. So the גמרא Gemara now says, you know,
tried to prove it from a משנה Mishna about what happens if
a person says, "This is my גט get if I die," and
that would be an example of אונס ones and whether we can
infer something about what would happen if he said, "This will be
my, this will be my גט get if I don't return," and
then he died. So the condition was met because of an אונס.
ones. And what would be the situation if he got sick? But
the גמרא Gemara said that maybe the real point of that was
not to tell you the issue of אונס ones but to tell
you the idea that a גט get cannot take effect after somebody
has died, אין גט לאחר מיתה. ein get achar misa. So let's
pick up from there. It's about exactly halfway down in the
דף. daf. והיא גופא קא משמע לן, Vehi gufa ka mashma lan,
the גמרא Gemara says, it's telling you that thing itself, דאין גט
לאחר מיתה. de'ein get achar misa. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
אין גט לאחר מיתה התנא ליה רישא? ein get achar misa hatana
lei reisha? The idea that a גט get doesn't take effect after
death, that's something that we knew from the beginning of that משנה.
Mishna. הרי זה גיטך אם מתי, Harei zeh gitich im mati, if
somebody says, "This is my גט get if I die," הרי זה
גיטך מחולי זה, Harei zeh gitich mecholi zeh, "This is my גט
get if I don't get better from this illness," הרי זה
גיטך לאחר מיתה Harei zeh gitich achar misa or "This is my
גט get after I die," לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, none
of those work because, and then he dies, he dies from the
illness he's in the middle of. So in all those cases, when
you say אם מתי im mati or מחולי זה, mecholi zeh, you're
not just saying a stipulation, when we learn גיטין Gittin we'll look
at this, but you're actually saying that's when it will take effect.
It will take effect when I die, it'll take effect when I
never get up from this illness. So in all those
cases לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. So we already know the
principle of
אין גט לאחר מיתה. ein get achar misa. So teaching you this
other case of if he says "If I don't return in twelve
months," presumably that's teaching you a new principle relating to the issue
about אונס, ones, about whether the fact that it has happened without,
outside of somebody's control is a factor or not. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, both of those are teaching you אין גט לאחר
מיתה, ein get achar misa, but you need to tell it to
me twice. Why do you need to tell it to me twice?
Because דילמא לאפוקי מרבותינו, dilma l'apokei merabboseinu, maybe it's to come to
say that the principle that a גט get doesn't take place after
death is to reject the position of רבותינו. Rabboseinu. What's רבותינו? Rabboseinu?
דתניא, Detanya, we learn a ברייתא: braita: רבותינו התירו להינשא, Rabboseinu hitiru
lenasei,
that even if somebody says "This is my גט get after I
die," our רבותינו, Rabboseinu, whoever that is, said she could get married.
How could she get married? What about אין גט לאחר מיתה? ein
get achar misa? So אמרינן מאן רבותינו, amrinan man rabboseinu,
who is our רבותינו? Rabboseinu? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, בי דינא דשרו משחא. Bei Dina Desharu Mishcha.
So this just proves to you that you go ahead and you
give too many קולות, kulos, you get labeled by it. So there
was a מסכת עבודה זרה, Masechet Avodah Zarah, there was a בית
דין beis din that reversed a principle that you cannot have the
oil produced by non-Jews. And they became labeled as the בי דינא
דשרו משחא, Bei Dina Desharu Mishcha, the בית דין beis din that
permitted the oil. And that was the בית דין beis din of
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. So the גמרא Gemara says it was them,
look at this, they're all being so מיקל, meikil, they permit oil,
they permit a גט. get. They were the ones that said that
if a person says, "This is my גט get when I die,"
that it actually works. Why is that? Let's take a look. סברי
לה כרבי יוסי, Savri lah k'Rabbi Yossi, or actually, no, I'm sorry,
that בית דין beis din wasn't רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, but that
בית דין beis din held like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. דאמר זמנו
של שטר מוכיח עליו, de'amar zmano shel shetar mochiach alav,
that if you have a date in a document, the purpose of
dating a document, why if you say "This will take effect in
twelve months from now," so why did you put a date in
the document? Maybe you should put the date when it takes effect.
Why did you put the date that it was written? So if
you're putting the date that it's written, the purpose of that is
to say that the גט get will take effect as of the
date in the document. So even if there's a condition and a
stipulation and you say "It'll take effect when I die," the fact
that you're also dating the document is saying but it really starts
taking effect retroactively as of now. So according to them, according to
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, right, there would be a גט לאחר מיתה
get achar misa as long as you had a date in the
document. And that's why you have to tell me the principle twice
of אין גט לאחר מיתה, ein get achar misa, to tell me
number one the general principle אין גט לאחר מיתה, ein get achar
misa, and number two, even if the document is
a
גט. get. So that
so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So that's why the examples
in this משנה Mishnah that speak about a guy who says if
in twelve months I don't return and he dies is not relevant
to the discussion of אונס. onus. The only purpose of discussing that
is to tell you the basic principle of אין גט לאחר מיתה
ein get l'achar misa and to tell to tell you twice to
tell you that that's true even when the document is dated. So
we don't have any relevant source for our question of whether יש
אונס בגיטין או אין אונס. yesh onus bigitin or ein onus. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואלא מסיפא. v'ela miseifa. Let's try to figure
it out from the end of that משנה. Mishnah. מעכשיו אם לא
באתי מכאן ועד שנים עשר חודש. Me'achshav im lo basi mikan v'ad
shenem asar chodesh. If somebody says explicitly I want the גט get
to take place as of now, it'll be effective as of now
if I don't return within twelve months. I mean you could understand
why somebody would make that condition so his wife would not be
left as an עגונה agunah if he doesn't return and she doesn't
know where he is. ומת בתוך שנים עשר חודש. Umes b'soch shenem
asar chodesh. And he dies in twelve months. So the condition was
met. He didn't return within the year. And it's not a גט
לאחר מיתה get l'achar misa because he said as of now. So
the condition was met. But the condition was only met because of
an אונס, onus, because he died, right, because he couldn't control it.
Okay, so what's the story? הרי זה גט. Harei zeh get. So
the גמרא Gemara says it's a גט. get. So you see that
the fact that there was an אונס onus does is not a
factor. We say the condition was met, we don't care if the
only reason it was met was because he died. אונס onus is
not a factor.
So does he he can eat תרומה Terumah the whole time?
I'm not talking about that, we'll worry about that when we get
to גיטין. Gittin. Okay, הרי זה גט. Harei zeh get. מת והוא
הדין לחולה. Mes v'hu hadin l'chola.
So presumably whether he died or whether he got sick, the principle
is that the fact that there was an אונס onus is not
a factor, right? As long as the condition was met, I don't
care whether there was an אונס, onus, whether there wasn't an אונס.
onus. All I care about was that the condition was met. מת
והוא הדין לחולה. Mes v'hu hadin l'chola. So it doesn't matter, died,
sick, whatever. גמרא Gemara says no, maybe the אונס onus is a
factor, but there are different types of אונס. onus. Some will be
a factor, some will not. Let's take a look. דילמא מת דוקא,
Dilma mes davka,
maybe only dying is not something that we would that would change
the conditions of the that would change whether how we assessed the
whether the conditions were met. מת דוקא דלא ניחא ליה דתיפול קמי
יבם. Mes davka d'lo nicha lei d'tipal kamei yavam. One of the
whole reasons a person would give a גט get to his wife,
right, if he's afraid he might die, one is that she wouldn't
be an עגונה, agunah, but the other is that even if he
knows he's going to die, he wants her to have a גט
get so she doesn't have to worry about ייבום, yibum, our entire
past מסכת. maseches. So therefore of course if he dies, he would
want the condition to be considered to be met. That's maybe one
of the reasons he's given her the גט get in the first
place. So that type of an אונס onus is not really even
such an אונס, onus, you know, that's exactly the type of thing
he might have anticipated and he would have wanted that to have
counted. One minute,
but if he got sick, that was something he never would have
anticipated and he would have wanted to be able to return and
to negate the condition. And therefore maybe it should not be held
against him the because it was out of his control. So now
the idea here that you look at אונס, onus, this is important
and this is going to be sort of the assumption of the
גמרא, Gemara, right, why should אונס onus change the thing? You basically
made a stipulation, the conditions were met, why should the fact that
it was outside of your control
matter?
So there's one of two ways of looking at it. One is
and what רש"י Rashi sort of quotes at the top of ג
עמוד א gimmel amud aleph is like well the Torah never holds
you culpable for an אונס. onus. Right, if a woman is raped,
she's not culpable, it's not her fault, okay. So and you know,
so basically אונס רחמנא פטריה. onus rachmana patrei. Now that seems a
little bit absurd because this isn't a question about blame and fault.
Right, this is a question about whether the conditions were met or
not. And also that wouldn't distinguish between something like dying or getting
sick if you know, if it's an objective thing that אונס onus
doesn't count, okay, then what should it matter or you know, what
you know, whether you would have won you know whether you were
thinking about the possibility of death or not thinking. So it seems
that what the גמרא Gemara is really getting at and this is
going to be the theme that runs through the גמרא Gemara is
not a general principle of אונס, onus, but a question about if
you make a condition, then it's a question about what you wanted.
So you know, you know under what circumstances did you want it
to take effect? So if you basically wanted to say I want
to have the ability to negate it by returning, you know, maybe
you would not have wanted it to take to take effect if
you would have been trying to return but you couldn't because you
got sick. So maybe again the reason אונס onus should matter is
we should sort of say that was never the conditions that you
had actually intended in the first place. Dying, that was a condition
that you probably were thinking about that you probably did intend. But
getting sick, those weren't the conditions you were thinking about and therefore
that should not be defined when the גט get takes effect. So
it's all a question of what your דעת da'as was. Of course
the problem with that is you cannot run a legal system trying
to guess somebody's דעת da'as in their mind. The general principle is
דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim shebalev einam devarim, okay, and we will
see unless it's something that is very obvious and evident. However, I
do want to just say again I don't want to get too
detailed and complicated, but normally the principle of דברים שבלב אינם דברים.
devarim shebalev einam devarim. is the רמב"ם Rambam says it and the
תוספות רי"ד, Tosafos Rid, much more of a principle when you're dealing
with two-sided transactions. I'm selling you something, so I can't say, oh,
well here's what I was thinking, you know? You're putting out money,
I'm giving you the object, the only thing that's relevant to that
transaction is information that is accessible by both sides, not things that's
hidden in our heads. But if it's a one-sided transaction, let's say
I give you a gift. Let's say I give you a gift,
which is you don't give me any money. I can say, well,
I never really wanted the gift to take effect in these cases.
You can say, hey, it's not fair. What do you mean fair?
It was a one-sided transaction. Or a גט, get, one-sided transaction, the
woman really doesn't have any choice in the matter. There what's going
on in my head might matter a little bit more, okay? But
that, so that seems to be what the issue here is, not
a general principle אונס onus doesn't count, you know, but a principle
about did I intend it in these circumstances? So the גמרא Gemara
says, yes, you would have intended it to take effect if you
had died. That was one of the things maybe you were even
thinking about or we could assume that. But if you got sick,
maybe those weren't the conditions and maybe it shouldn't take effect. Yes,
first Michael had a question. No, okay, Dov, what?
Yeah, so I appreciate the גמרא's Gemara insight that מיתה mesa is
לא ניחא ליה. lo nicha lei. Right.
Well, that's not exactly what it said, but okay, yeah.
No, but my question actually is what if the guy didn't have
a brother? Right.
So, under the
conditions that he's... right. Or let's say he had kids, right, you're
right. Okay, so all those things would have to be taken into
effect. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא
מהא. ela meha. So let's try to prove אין אונס בגט ein
onus be-get from the following case. דהוא דאמר להו, de-hu de-amar le-hu,
a person said to them, to witnesses: אי לא אתינא מכאן ועד
תלתין יומין, i lo asina mi-kan ve-ad tlasin yomin, and if I
don't return within thirty days, ליהוי גיטא, le-havei gitta, let it be
a גט. get. I don't know who he said it to, maybe
the witnesses, and he gave it to his wife. And he said
if I don't return. אתא בסוף תלתין יומין, asa be-sof tlasin yomin,
he came at the end of thirty days ופסקיה מברא, u-paska mabara,
but like a river got in the way,
he wasn't able to cross the river. Okay, so there he was,
he was trying to negate the condition of the גט. get. He
was trying to return, but clearly but he couldn't. He missed his
last taxi out of town or the last train out of town.
אמר להו: amar le-hu: חזו דאתאי חזו דאתאי. chazu de-asai chazu de-asai.
He yelled across the river: I'm coming, I'm coming, I'm coming, you
know, but the clock was running out and he wasn't able to
cross the river in time.
So his רצון ratzon is known, but he didn't act on it.
Right. And it's clear that in that case he wanted the גט
get to be annulled. But there was an אונס. onus. So אמר
שמואל: amar Shmuel: לאו שמיה מתיא. lav shemei masia. It's very nice,
but he didn't come, so it doesn't matter. And therefore the גט,
get, you know, the גט get takes effect, right? The fact that
it was an אונס onus is irrelevant. So that's maybe... so of
course it's funny because you know, this is a position of רבא,
Rava, so רבא's Rava learning it from שמואל. Shmuel. Doesn't tell you
where שמואל Shmuel knows it from, but okay, here we have an
example from a case of שמואל Shmuel that אונס onus doesn't matter.
So the גמרא Gemara says: no, maybe you can't generalize. ודלמא אונסא
דשכיח שאני. ve-dilma unsa de-shiyach shani. Maybe a common type of an
אונס onus is different. That can't matter, it can't matter if it's
something that, you know, this is something you could have anticipated. דכיון
דאיבעי ליה לאתנויי ולא אתני, de-keivan de-ibayei lei le-asnu-ei ve-lo asni, you
should have stipulated. You should have said: this will be a גט
get if I don't return unless I am held up by things
out of my control. Because that's a normal type of a thing
that could have occurred. So since you didn't stipulate, you're stuck with
what you said. איהו דאפסיד אנפשיה, ihu de-afsidei nafshiyei, you're stuck with
it, which basically means that we... so the אונס onus here, again,
it's similar to the idea of: well, maybe you wanted it to
take effect if you died, right? Or the fact that this is
something you could have anticipated and you didn't mention it means that
that's going to be assumed included in your דעת daas regardless of
whether the reason you couldn't come because you missed your train. So
the question is going to be something you wouldn't have anticipated, okay,
like you were, I don't know, you were struck by lightning. Okay,
so missing the train is something you anticipated. But you could have
said: if I can't come because of an act of God. Do
you have to say if I can't come because of an act
of God, because I'm struck by lightning? Or is that something that
no normal person would have ever anticipated and we should say that
wasn't in your דעת daas and therefore that case you obviously would
have not wanted it to be like your condition was met.
If the river is a case of אונסא דשכיח, unsa de-shiyach, right?
And therefore since you could have anticipated it, therefore you can't say,
oh, I didn't want it to take effect in these circumstances, or
something like that, right? Okay.
So
then she... then it wouldn't be חל. chal.
It's not... no, the גט get is חל chal because if you
didn't want it to take effect under these circumstances, you should have
said something. You should have said something.
You should have said, unless there's traffic.
Right. This is a גט get unless if I don't return unless
there's really bad traffic. Exactly, exactly. So that's a common thing, you
should have anticipated it, you didn't, it meant you wanted it to
take place regardless.
No matter what.
No matter what. But what about something that no normal person would
have anticipated? What's the story here? So you see it's all about
the question of דעת. daas. So the גמרא Gemara basically concedes that
we don't have a good proof to that idea. Now just because
you don't have a good proof, you could have said fine, you
don't have a proof, but רבא Rava nevertheless has this position like
דברים שבלב אינם דברים, dvarim she-ba-lev einam dvarim, end of story. story.
But the גמרא Gemara rather than just saying it's a principle that's
like makes sense as a legal principle, why why should we care
what's going on in your head, the גמרא Gemara actually makes it
a policy principle, a policy position. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. אלא רבא סברא דנפשיה קאמר, Ella Rava sevara d'nafshei ka'amar,
רבא Rava is started up on his own. He doesn't have another
source. But again you could think it up on your own that
that's the legal principle. But the גמרא's Gemara going to say he
thought it up on his own and that this should be that's
אין אונס בגיטין ain ones b'gittin and that this needs to be
the policy. Why does this need to be the policy? Because משום
צנועות ומשום פרוצות mishum tznuos u'mishum prutzos because of women that are
overly צנועה, tznuah, meaning overly careful and cautious in terms of the
question about whether they can go ahead and marry another man, and
women that are overly... what's a good word for פרוצות? prutzos? Licentious?
Anyway, now, now, mean you want to say aggressive? Mean you want
to say aggressive? Licentious?
All right, anyway, too ready, too ready to get married to another
man. Okay, because if you basically, if you have to worry if,
if אונס ones makes a difference, you'll never know whether the condition
really was met, because you'll never know, it looks like it was
met, but maybe there was some, maybe he was struck by lightning.
So משום צנועות, mishum tznuos, דאי אמרת לא הוי גט, de'ee amrat
lo hevei get, if you say that it won't be a גט
get in those cases when there was an אונס ones even though
it looks like the condition was met. So top of ג׳ עמוד
א׳, Gimmel Amud Aleph, זימנין דלא אונס, zimnin d'lo ones, there'll be
times that won't be an אונס, ones, most of the times, 99.9%
of the
times, okay, וסברה דאונס, v'savrah d'ones, and she'll say well I don't
know if I can get remarried, maybe he was struck by lightning
and that and therefore it's not like it wouldn't have been the
condition wouldn't have been met because maybe it was only because of
an אונס. ones. ומעגנא ויתבא, u'me'aguna v'yasva, and she'll be an עגונה
agunah and she'll sit and she won't remarry when she totally should
remarry. ומשום פרוצות, u'mishum prutzos, and we also have to worry about
the opposite, women who are too ready to marry another man. דאי
אמרת לא הוי גיטא, de'ee amrat lo hevei gitta, if because of
an אונס ones would say that the condition wasn't met, זימנין דאונס,
zimnin d'ones, there'll be times that it was an אונס, ones, and
תוספות Tosafot sort of sticks in, you know, that not only there
will be an אונס ones but there's reason to believe there was
an אונס. ones. So therefore the normal conduct should be that you
should not get married because there was a good reason to believe
there was an אונס. ones. ואמרה לאו אונס, v'amrah lav ones, and
she'll say oh no it wasn't an אונס, ones, ואזלה ומינסבא, v'azla
u'minsva, and she'll go ahead and get married ונמצא גט בטל ובניה
ממזרים, v'nimtza get batel u'vaneha mamzerim, and then it'll turn out that
it really was never a גט get and her kids are ממזרים.
mamzerim. So you cannot run a society with saying you never know
if the conditions were met because you never know what happened in
a faraway country and you know and who knows whether there was
an אונס ones or not. Then everybody's going to be acting either
too cautiously or too incautious... anyway, anyway, uncautious,
so therefore we basically have to say we ignore any issues of
אונס. ones. Now again, you could have said it from a legal
principle like דברים שבלב אינם דברים. d'varim she'blev ainam d'varim. But he's
saying it as a policy position. So the גמרא Gemara says you're
saying it as a policy position? So what are you... if the
real legal principle is that אונס ones matters, how do you ignore
that? Just because for policy we can't factor it in? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ומשום צנועות ומשום פרוצות, u'mishum tznuos u'mishum
prutzos,
because of policy conditions about people that will be too cautious or
too
in- what's the word? Incautious? Anyway, anyway,
uncautious, so שרינן אשת איש לעלמא? sharinan eshes ish l'alma? We would
go ahead and we would make it a גט? get? We're going
to say it's always going to be a גט. get. We don't
care about אונס. ones. Even though אונס ones should negate it? How
could you make it a גט get just because of policy? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אין, in, yea, כל דמקדש אדעתא דרבנן מקדש.
kol d'mekadesh ada'ata d'rabanan mekadesh. Anyone who gets married gets married on
the basis of the rabbis because you're all working not, you know,
we don't live in a world of biblical Judaism, we live in
a world of rabbinic Judaism. So any time you do this type
of a legal act it's understood to be sort of in the
through the way the rabbis have understood it and framed it. ואפקעינהו
רבנן לקידושין מיניה, v'afkinhu rabanan l'kidushin minei,
and the rabbis can retroactively say under these conditions even though legally
it shouldn't be a גט, get, we'll recognize it as a גט.
get. How do we recognize it as a גט? get? By retroactively
uprooting the קידושין. kidushin. So this is one of the classic סוגיות
sugyos of הפקעת קידושין, hafka'as kidushin, of uprooting קידושין. kidushin.
And, you know obviously it's discussed a lot today in issues of
עגונה. agunah. An important point to recognize about this and about its
general relevance is two things. Number one is it's not like a
case-by-case basis, right? It's a sort of a very systematic position like
it's sort of making a statement. Every time there's a גט get
under these circumstances it's הפקעת קידושין. hafka'as kidushin. It's not like oh
this is a one particular circumstance that this one woman is an
עגונה, agunah, let's do הפקעת קידושין hafka'as kidushin for you. No, it's
sort of making something that's a general rule and the rule by
the way is in place from the moment that people are getting
married based on this whole idea אדעתא דרבנן מקדש. ada'ata d'rabanan mekadesh.
So from the very moment that you get married you got married
with these rules in place that under these circumstances retroactively it would
be הפקעת קידושין. hafka'as kidushin. That's point number one. Point number two
is that there's a גט get here. It might be not a
good גט get because the condition wasn't met but there's a גט.
get. And רש״י Rashi consistently looks at that. If you take a
look at רש״י Rashi for example רש״י Rashi says, כל
המקדש, kol hamekadesh, the first narrow line, כל המקדש אישה אדעתא. kol
hamekadesh isha ada'ata. הנהיגו חכמי ישראל בישראל הוא מקדשה שיהיו קיימים קידושין
לפי דברי חכמים ויהיו בטלים לפי דברי חכמים על ידי גיטין שהכשירו
חכמים hinhigu chachamei Yisrael be-Yisrael hu mekadesha she-yihyu kayamim kiddushin le-fi divrei
chachamim ve-yihyu betelim le-fi divrei chachamim al yedei gittin she-hikshiru chachamim
through this גט. get. And if you look at the next רש"י,
Rashi, אפקינו רבנן לקידושין כשיבוא גט כזה אחריהן. Afkinu Rabbanan le-kiddushin kshe-yavo
get kazeh achareihen.
So this is a principle that the רשב"א Rashba elaborates on and
he says even if we could do הפקעת קידושין hafkas kiddushin we
are not going to do a like a bold exercise of power.
We're not going to say, yes we're walking in and we're nullifying
the קידושין. kiddushin. We basically, that's the sort of secret mechanism that
operates behind the scenes. But to do it directly would like undermine
the institutions, right? So therefore if we're going to use it, it's
going to be a hidden mechanism and you need what the רשב"א
Rashba calls a סרך גט, srach get, a semblance of a גט.
get. So you need a גט get even though the גט get
doesn't work because the condition wasn't met or there's another case in
גיטין Gittin about a גט get that somebody annulled, okay, and but
nevertheless that's what that's like what I call the fig leaf. Okay,
you need that type of a fig leaf and then the הפקעת
קידושין hafkas kiddushin is the hidden mechanism that allows it to work,
but we're not just going to go straight and walk out and
say yeah we don't like this case הפקעת קידושין. hafkas kiddushin. Okay,
that's only like the mechanism that operates behind the scenes. By the
way, we just finished יבמות Yevamos where we had all that discussion
of believing in עד אחד ed echad which violates normal principles of
what type of testimony you need to determine somebody is dead. How
do you deal with that? So one explanation is like well, the
woman investigates it so much and there's so much circumstantial evidence that's
good enough. But the רשב"א Rashba says building himself on a רש"י
Rashi that actually that also works for the הפקעת קידושין. hafkas kiddushin.
But what's the fig leaf there in all those cases in יבמות?
Yevamos? Here the fig leaf is a גט. get. What's the fig
leaf in those cases in יבמות Yevamos that we've been doing for
the last few weeks? What makes us be able to say, we're
not just, do we have one person? Right. So we're not walking
out and announcing and saying well we don't know what happened to
the husband but we're going to do הפקעת קידושין. hafkas kiddushin. No,
we're going to say we believe the עד. ed. But the fact
is that doesn't really work because it's only one עד. ed. Okay,
so behind the scenes we're going to do הפקעת קידושין hafkas kiddushin
but upfront we're going to say we believe the עד. ed. So
that's how the רשב"א Rashba explains the circumstances for הפקעת קידושין hafkas
kiddushin and that's very much reinforced by רש"י Rashi in this סוגיא
sugya that consistently repeats when there's a גט get like this, when
there's a גט get like this, the rabbis will do הפקעת קידושין.
hafkas kiddushin. Okay, so that's the principle of הפקעת קידושין. hafkas kiddushin.
By the way, little תוספות, Tosafos, אדעתא דרבנן מקדש לכן אומרים בשעת
קידושין כדת משה וישראל ada'ata de-rabbanan mekadesh lachen omrim be-sha'as kiddushin kedas
Moshe ve-Yisrael
which is nowhere in the גמרא Gemara but the practice of saying
כדת משה וישראל kedas Moshe ve-Yisrael signals משה Moshe is תורה דאורייתא
Torah De-oraisa and ישראל, Yisrael, the Jewish people represented by the rabbis,
is the רבנן, Rabbanan, אדעתא דרבנן מקדש. ada'ata de-rabbanan mekadesh. So we
signal that by the saying of כדת משה וישראל. kedas Moshe ve-Yisrael.
Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara. So that's how it works. Really
in policy we should consider אונס, ones, I mean in legally we
should consider אונס, ones, but in policy we can't so we use
הפקעת קידושין hafkas kiddushin to make the גט get good. אמר ליה
רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, said רבינא Ravina to
רב אשי: Rav Ashi: תינח דקדש בכספא. Teynach de-kadesh be-chaspa. That's fine
if you married with money because then we could say the
rabbis הפקר בית דין הפקר, Hefker beis din hefker, made the money
ownerless and therefore that's how the mechanism they used to uproot the
קידושין. kiddushin. But קדש בביאה מאי איכא למימר? kadesh be-via mai ika
le-meimar? Let's say it was קידושי ביאה. kiddushei via. So what are
they going to do? The physical reality of having had sex, what
can they say about that? How can they change that? How can
they make that not an act of קידושין? kiddushin? So the גמרא
Gemara says no, שויוה רבנן לבעילתו בעילת זנות. shavyuha Rabbanan le-veilaso veilas
zenus. They can change the context. They can say it's only marital
sex that is a act of קידושין, kiddushin, right? A lot of
people have sex, it has nothing to do with קידושין, kiddushin, right?
It's זנות, zenus, it's pre-marital sex, it's non-marital sex. So what the
rabbis will say is who determines what the context is? You might
have said oh I wanted it to be marital sex but the
society might not see it that way or the reverse, right? You
might see it as marital sex, society sees it as זנות. zenus.
So who determines what's how what is the context that defines the
nature of the act? And here it says we the rabbis are
the ones that determine.
And retroactively of course right, they've been living together for 20 years,
going to שול, shul, they've got kids, they've got the בר ובת
מצוה, bar and bat mitzvahs, they've got their family membership and now
retroactively we're going to say no you've been living in sin all
that time. Okay, so that's still a big חידוש, chiddush, I admit.
Okay, but that's the point. The point is that we can retroactively
redefine how we looked at that act of sex. Yes.
What if they had witnesses that
he
intended to marry
by קידושי ביאה kiddushei via and we have כוונה kavana to do
it as you know you're right that's a good point because standard
I mean it's a question about the exact role of witnesses by
קידושי ביאה kiddushei via but but you're right there are witnesses there
even if they're not seeing the exact act they're sort of seeing
you know them go into the room or whatever.
Yeah so you're right that's a good point we would have to
say that the rabbis sort of superimpose their understanding and their way
of framing the context that overrides what was the witnesses how the
witnesses were informed. If I be that they said that to you
but it doesn't matter what they said that's now... refuse to, you
know, we don't look at it that way. We're going to say
that that was just a farce. They might have said that, but
it's a farce and it really was just זנות. znus. And you're
right, and that overrides even how the witnesses were informed.
And that wouldn't be the רוב rov of the cases
of קידושי ביאה, Kiddushei Biah, that's true. Now I do want to
say,
by the way,
there's a famous alternate interpretation of this that רש״י Rashi quotes, that
might be reflected in a רמב״ם, Rambam, that actually says that the
reason the גמרא Gemara prefers, says קידושי כסף Kiddushei Kesef is easier
to redefine is not because of הפקר בית דין הפקר, Hefker Beis
Din Hefker, but an idea that קידושי כסף Kiddushei Kesef is only
דרבנן, Derabanan, that the only thing that's קידושי תורה Kiddushei Torah is
actually ביאה. Biah. Okay, but then, and now that's shocking because, you
know, you learn קידושין Kiddushin and it always seems like קידושי כסף
Kiddushei Kesef is דאורייתא, De'oraisa, it seems like the woman would be
considered אשת איש דאורייתא, Eishes Ish De'oraisa, all these types of things.
But that's one way that's interpretation of קידושי כסף, Kiddushei Kesef, that's
only דרבנן. Derabanan. So, but קידושי ביאה Kiddushei Biah is דאורייתא. De'oraisa.
So what's the answer then, if קידושי ביאה Kiddushei Biah is דאורייתא?
De'oraisa? So we're still going to say אפקיעינהו רבנן לקידושין מיניה? Afki'inhu
Rabbanan Lekiddushin Minei? So רש״י Rashi says, no, this interpretation would say
that the way that works is not saying that retroactively we redefine
or whatever. It's actually saying that we don't want people to get
married with קידושי ביאה. Kiddushei Biah. You might remember there's a גמרא
Gemara that says that they gave lashes to people that got married
with קידושי ביאה Kiddushei Biah because it was פריצות pritzus and inappropriate
and so on. So that means from the very outset, we never
recognize קידושי ביאה, Kiddushei Biah, it was we only recognize it as
זנות. znus. So קידושי ביאה Kiddushei Biah is זנות, znus, קידושי כסף
Kiddushei Kesef is דרבנן, Derabanan, so according to this, the only קידושין
Kiddushin that would be דאורייתא De'oraisa that we couldn't say הפקעת קידושין
Hafka'as Kiddushin for would be שטר. shtar. But other than that, it's
either קידושי דרבנן Kiddushei Derabanan that we can control or קידושי ביאה
Kiddushei Biah which we never recognize. But רש״י Rashi doesn't like this
at all. And just to show you the last line of this
רש״י, Rashi, you go back about eight lines up from the narrow
lines. He says, ומפרשים דשוויה רבנן, Umefarshim Deshavyei Rabbanan, line starts with
the word רבנן. Rabbanan. שוויה רבנן לכל מקדש בביאה בעילת זנות, Shavyei
Rabbanan Lechol Mekadesh Bebiah Beilas Znus, that every קידושי ביאה Kiddushei Biah
is בעילת זנות, beilas znus, that we refuse to recognize it. טעות
גמור הוא. Toos gomur hu. ובא להתיר אשת איש המקדשת בביאה בלא
גט מן הטעם הזה. Uba Lehatir Eishes Ish Hamikadeshes Bebiah Beloget Min
Hatam Hazeh. And you'll basically say that a woman that had קידושי
ביאה Kiddushei Biah could just walk away, okay, מן הטעם הזה ולא
מצינו זאת בתלמוד. Min hatam hazeh velo matzinu zos batalmud. Right? So
basically רש״י Rashi strongly rejects this. But it's a fascinating different read
of the גמרא, Gemara, that קידושי כסף Kiddushei Kesef is דרבנן, Derabanan,
קידושי ביאה Kiddushei Biah is never really recognized. Okay, a very different
read of אפקעת קידושין Hafka'as Kiddushin and what's going on in the
גמרא. Gemara. Back to the גמרא. Gemara. Oh boy, we are already
falling behind, it's only day two. איכא דאמרי, Ika Deamri, some say.
So that's the end of that discussion, that in principle אונס ones
matters. Okay, certain types of אונס ones matters that you couldn't have
anticipated, but in policy we reject it. איכא דאמרי, Ika Deamri, others
say, אמר רבא וכן לענין גיטין. Amar Rava Vchein Linyan Gittin. He
says actually, אונס ones matters actually, not just in principle but in
practice. We will factor in concerns of אונס ones by an issue
of a גט get and a condition on a גט. get. אלמא
קסבר רבא יש אונס בגיטין. Alman Kasavar Rava Yesh Ones Begittin. מתיבי,
Maseivei, I'll ask you on this. הרי זה גיטך אם לא באתי
מכאן ועד שנים עשר חודש. Hareis Zeh Gittech Im Lo Basi Mikan
Vad Shneim Asar Chodesh. We're going to go through everything we did
yesterday. ומת בתוך שנים עשר חודש, Umeis Besoch Shneim Asar Chodesh, if
I don't return in 12 months and he doesn't return because he
died. ומת בתוך הרי אינו גט, Umeis Besoch Harei Eino Get, it's
not a גט. get. מת הוא דאינו גט, Meis Hu Deino Get,
it's not a גט get because he died. ואין גט לאחר מיתה.
Vein Get Leachar Misah. חלה הרי זה גט, Chala Hareis Zeh Get,
if he got sick it would be, even though there was an
אונס, ones, it wouldn't matter, the condition would still be considered to
have been met. So you see אין אונס בגיטין? Ein Ones Begittin?
No. לעולם אימא לך חלה נמי אינו גט. Leolam Eima Lach Chala
Nami Eino Get. If he got sick it's also not a גט
get because the אונס ones does matter and it would negate the
תנאי. tnai. Okay, אלא היא
גופא קמשמע לן. Ela Hi Gufa Kamashma Lan. But the point of
this is not to tell you the issue of אונס, ones, it's
to tell you the point itself that a גט get doesn't take
effect after dying, דאין גט לאחר מיתה. Dein Get Leachar Misah. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אין גט לאחר מיתה, Ein Get Leachar Misah,
to tell me a גט get doesn't take effect after dying? הא
תנא ליה רישא. Ha Tana Lei Reisha. We learned it in the
beginning of the משנה. Mishna. So, right, and then it had that
whole case which we didn't requote here. But says, no, דילמא לאפוקי
מדרבותינו. Diyalma Lafokei Midraboseinu. No, maybe it had to tell me twice
to tell me that even though there's a date written in the
גט, get, it doesn't take effect retroactively, אין גט לאחר מיתה Ein
Get Leachar Misah even with a date written in. So that's not
relevant to the question of אונס. ones. תא שמע, Ta Shma, come
and hear. מעכשיו אם לא באתי מכאן ועד שנים עשר חודש. Meachshav
Im Lo Basi Mikan Vad Shneim Asar Chodesh. If he says it's
a גט get from as of now if I don't return in
12 months. ומת בתוך שנים עשר חודש הרי זה גט. Umeis Besoch
Shneim Asar Chodesh Hareis Zeh Get. And he dies, it's a גט.
get. So even though he died and the condition was met because
he died,
it's still we don't factor in אונס. ones. מאי לאו הוא הדין
לחלה? Mai Lav Hu Hadin Lechala? Isn't it the same true about
getting sick? And you see that אונס ones is not a factor?
גמרא Gemara says, לא, מת דוקא. Lo, Meis Davka. Only dying is
אונס ones not a factor. דלא ניחא ליה דתיפול קמי יבם, Delo
Nichla Lei Detipol Kamei Yavam, because that's something that maybe he specifically
wanted it to take effect in those cases. But something like getting
sick, where he wouldn't have wanted it to take effect, and that
we could say if it was out of his control, that should
be a factor. So תא שמע, Ta Shma, מההוא דאמר להו, Mehahu
Deamar Lehu, a person said, אי לא אתינא מכאן ועד תלתין יומין,
Ei Lo Asina Mikan Vad Tlatin Yomin, if I don't return in
30 days, להוי גט. Lehavei Get.
אתא בסוף תלתין יומין, Asa Besof Tlatin Yomin, he came back within
30 days. ופסק מברא, Upasak Mabra, but he was, you know, he
was stopped by a river. ואמר להו חזו דאתאי חזו דאתאי. Veamar
Lehu Chazu Deasai Chazu Deasai. Look I'm coming I'm coming! דאמר שמואל
לא שמיה אתיה. de'amar Shmuel lo shmai atiya. It's not it's very
nice that you say you're coming, but you didn't come. Okay, so
you see אין אונס בגיטין, ein ones b'gittin, and that goes against
this version of רבא Rava that says יש אונס. yesh ones. So
here we're seeing אונס ones doesn't matter. But she says no, maybe
אונס דשכיח שאני. ones d'shchiach shani. No, there it doesn't matter because
that's something you could have anticipated. דכיון דאיבעי ליה לאתנויי ולא אתני
איהו דאפסיד אנפשיה. d'keivan d'ibei lei l'asnu-ei v'lo asni ihu d'afsid anafshei.
Since you could have
anticipated
it
and you didn't, then we say, then obviously you can't say, oh
this I never meant for it to happen in this case. If
you should have thought about that and said and explicitly excluded it.
But something that you really wouldn't have anticipated, maybe that will be
a factor. So then it becomes a big question. Now what we
have two possible positions of רבא. Rava. אין אונס בגיטין, ein ones
b'gittin, which is the one that works in society as the גמרא
Gemara says, because you have the פרוצות perutzos and the צנועות. tznuos.
Or יש אונס בגיטין, yesh ones b'gittin, which means that we're never
going to know what the whether the גט get really took effect
or not. So there's a long תוספות Tosafot and he basically says
that we conclude אין אונס בגיטין, ein ones b'gittin, which is the
obviously the position that you really have to conclude in terms of
societal. But at the end of תוספות Tosafot he says, there might
be cases where really everybody would concede an אונס ones does matter,
and then it sort of just throws the whole thing into a
confusion. So even in the end of the story, there remains a
little bit of a question. Are there some types of אונס ones
like what? Whatever, a middle case. Not something that you totally should
have anticipated, not something that's totally out of your control, but like
תוספות Tosafot says, like if it was something that you never would
have anticipated, like again being struck by lightning, maybe everybody would agree
there יש אונס בגיטין. yesh ones b'gittin. Okay? So anyway, it remains
a it remains a a question. And of course, as with the
גמרא Gemara said, the societal implications of having to worry about an
אונס ones that we have no knowledge about and so on, obviously
would be drastic. Okay, so it's not a totally clear conclusion of
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes on, so we
put all of that aside, we're done with this whole אונס ones
discussion, back to our basic point of the משנה, Mishna, that בתולות
betulos get married on a Wednesday so they can have sex Wednesday
night, so if there needs to be a court case Thursday morning,
the husband can come to the court. But it was Wednesday and
not Sunday because three days to prepare for the wedding.
Even though they had a whole year to do it.
They had a year to prepare the trousseau, he had three days
to get the wedding feast ready. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר רב שמואל בר יצחק, amar Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak,
לא שנו אלא מתקנת עזרא ואילך. lo shanu ela mi-takanas Ezra v'eilach.
This is only that it's on Wednesdays once the תקנה takana of
עזרא Ezra that we'd have regular courts sitting on Mondays and Thursdays.
שאין בתי דינים קבועין אלא בשני ובחמישי, she'ein batei dinin k'vu-in ela
b'sheni u-vachamishi, that the regular courts are only Mondays and Thursdays. אבל
קודם תקנת עזרא, aval kodem takanas Ezra, beforehand, שבתי דינים קבועין בכל
יום, she-batei dinin k'vu-in b'chol yom, that there was a בית דין
beit din every single day, אשה נישאת בכל יום, ishah nisas b'chol
yom, she would get married any day because no day would matter.
Now תוספות Tosafot asks, before we get on in the גמרא, Gemara,
I don't understand, תקנת עזרא takanas Ezra said you should have בתי
דינים batei dinin come fewer times? Before עזרא Ezra it was coming
every day, and עזרא Ezra said no, only do it Tuesday and
Thursday? Maybe it's like יתרו, Yitro, נבל תבל, navol tivol, you gotta
cut down on your workload. No, but תוספות Tosafot says no. So
תוספות Tosafot has two interpretations. One is תקנת עזרא takanas Ezra said,
don't come every day, but go only come Tuesdays Mondays and Thursdays,
but go to all the villages, right, בתי דינים בכל העיירות, batei
dinin b'chol ha'ayarot, meaning maybe they met every day but only in
the cities. And עזרא Ezra said, stop coming every day, come only
Mondays and Thursdays, but on Mondays and Thursdays you should go to
the villages as well. The other interpretation of תוספות Tosafot is, is
that when it says they would meet every day, it meant that
they would put together an ad hoc בית דין beit din when
you needed it on a daily basis. And עזרא's Ezra תקנה takana
was to say no more ad hoc בתי דינים, batei dinin, there's
going to be regular בתי דין batei din with regular hours and
that's going to be on Mondays and Thursdays. Okay, so that's interesting
thinking about what עזרא Ezra might have done. But in any way,
what he's saying is when it was true that it was no
particular special special thing about a Monday and a Thursday, then you
could go get married any day they would get married. So the
גמרא Gemara says קודם
תקנת עזרא, kodem takanas Ezra, right?
Well, we'll talk about that. קודם תקנת עזרא, kodem takanas Ezra, before
עזרא, Ezra, מאי דהוה הוה? mai d'hava hava? Who cares? That's old
ancient history, right? The גמרא Gemara is basically completely unconcerned with history.
What does history matter? תורה Torah matters, הלכה halacha matters, history doesn't
matter. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. אי
איכא בתי דינים דקבועין האידנא, ei ika batei dinin di-k'vu-in idna,
if nowadays you would have regular בתי דינים batei dinin on every
day, or we could say the opposite, if you'd have no קבוע
kavu-a בית דין, beit din, if it would always be ad hoc,
but if nowadays the circumstances changed and there's nothing special about Monday
and Thursday, then כקודם תקנת עזרא, k'kodem takanas Ezra, it would be
like before תקנת עזרא takanas Ezra and אשה נישאת בכל יום, ishah
nisas b'chol yom, and a woman could get married on any day.
Okay now before we turn the page and say what about the
three days needed to prepare, right, because that was another factor, okay,
but the בית דין beit din factor the גמרא Gemara says that
would not limit you, you could get married on any day. So
תוספות Tosafot says like Michael, what about Friday? בתי דינים batei dinin
don't you can't convene a בית דין beit din on שבת. Shabbat.
And people might be curious might not know that the מנהג minhag
in אשכנז Ashkenaz in the Middle Ages was to have weddings late
Friday afternoon. Anybody want to know why?
So you can make it into your שבת Shabbat meal.
So you can people were poor and you could make it into
your שבת Shabbat meal. wedding meal, okay, which led to interesting הלכה
halachic discussions. For example, we're going to get to a גמרא Gemara
about can you have sex for the first time on שבת, Shabbos,
if the woman is a virgin and breaking the hymen and so
on. In אשכנז Ashkenaz they would do it every single time. Number
one. Number two is they would wind up playing, having the wedding
music played on שבת Shabbos by non-Jews. Okay, because you start the
wedding party and they would continue to have the wedding music being
played Friday night, so it gets to the whole issue of אמירה
לגוי amira l'goi and having non-Jews play music on שבת. Shabbos. Okay,
there's a whole thing there about אמירה לגוי.
amira l'goi. At least mentioned before שבת. Shabbos.
All right, what? What? You mentioned
תוספות. Tosafot. I mean, some of that is mentioned in the- no,
the wedding music is in the רמ"א, Rema, but I don't know
if it's in תוספות. Tosafot. Anyway, alright, whatever, but you have to
deal with that. Even אמירה לגוי amira l'goi before שבת Shabbos isn't
always allowed if he goes ahead and does it on שבת. Shabbos.
Anyway.
So the non-Jewish organist in the Reform synagogue.
Right, right. So, all right, we're not- stop.
Now, but look at this תוספות, Tosafot, but how about this issue
that there's no בית דין beis din on שבת? Shabbos? So how
could you get married on Friday? There's no בית דין beis din
that's possible the next day. So look at תוספות. Tosafot. איכא דבעי
למידק Ika d'ba'ei l'mideik נראה לרי nireh l'Ri דמכל מקום d'mikol makom
אין לישא בשישי ein lisa b'shishi דאין דנין בשבת d'ein danin b'shabbos
ואתה נוהג לישא אף בשישי. v'ata noheg lisa af b'shishi. And it's
not only אף בשישי, af b'shishi, that would be very common. משום
דאין בתי דינים קבועים mishum d'ein batei dinim kvuim ואם יש לו
טענת בתולים v'im yesh lo tanas besulim יכול לקבול בשבת yachol likbol
b'shabbos לפני שלושה lifnei shlosha כמו בשאר ימות השבוע. kmo b'sh'ar yemos
ha-shavua.
He basically says there wouldn't really be a בית דין beis din
nowadays that we're going to convene. What you would do is you
would register a complaint. And that you could register a complaint in
front of three people even on שבת, Shabbos, that's not a דין.
din. So you can take care of that even on שבת. Shabbos.
ועוד V'od לפירוש הקונטרס l'ferush ha-kuntres דוקא בימיהם davka b'yameihem קבעו יום
הנישואין kavu yom ha-nisuim משום שעל ידי כך mishum she'al yedei kach
יתפרסם הדבר yitparsem ha-davar ויבואו עדים. v'yavou eidim.
We would want to get witnesses and we'd want to actually like
prosecute her for actually committing adultery, okay? ויבואו עדים v'yavou eidim מתוך
שמתעסקים בבית דין mitoch she-misa'askim b'beis din ואין צריך למיחש להכי. v'ein
tzarich l'meichash l'hachi. Now we're not trying to prosecute anybody for adultery.
Like if we had to deal with it, we might deal with
it in terms of the question about how much is the כתובה,
kesubah, was the קידושין kiddushin א מקח טעות, a mekach taus, but
we would not be dealing with this whole need for a whole
בית דין beis din in order to try to get witnesses for,
you know, for adultery. So therefore תוספות Tosafot says the need nowadays
for the בית דין beis din is not the same. Because even
the things we want to address we can either just by registering
a complaint without a formal בית דין, beis din, or we certainly
don't need a בית דין beis din like in רש"י's Rashi's sense
of trying to produce witnesses about adultery, that's not our focus.
But you would want to have witnesses of adultery
so you could pay her less for the כתובה, kesubah, wouldn't you?
Yeah, but that might- it doesn't require the same type of witnesses
and same type of a formal בית דין. beis din. I mean
we're not trying to get- it's not a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos
that we're dealing with, okay? But you're right, I mean there are
cases, but that's what תוספות Tosafot said before, that you can register
the complaint and get started with that after שבת. Shabbos.
But if it was really דיני נפשות dinei nefashos
you would have to go to twenty-three. I understand. We'll see about
that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, you say that if there's not a- if a
בית דין beis din is not specifically on Thursday, any day is
okay, and תוספות Tosafot says, you know, besides תוספות's Tosafot's point about
Friday, but what a minute, what about the three days that you
need to prepare? הא בעינן שקדו, Ha ba'inan shakdu, don't you need
the fact that the rabbis were sort of conscientious, you know, concerned
with the- with Jewish women to make sure that they had- that
the grooms spent three days preparing for the wedding? So the גמרא
Gemara says טרח ליה, tarach lei, fine. You can get married any
day provided that you have spent three days getting the wedding feast
ready. We're not going to force a particular day on you, what
we're going to force on you is insist on you that you
invest three days in getting everything ready.
You get all the caterers and all that and you'll be good.
Exactly, okay. So מאי שקדו, Mai shakdu, which basically means the whole
idea of this פרק perek about Wednesday in practice stops being the
case because, you know, there's not בתי דינים קבועים batei dinim kvuim
and all you have to do is make sure that you put
together a nice wedding party. Okay, מאי שקדו. Mai shakdu. So that's
in terms of- nowadays the Wednesday thing doesn't really apply. Now we
get back to this issue about שקדו shakdu and we're going to
turn to another like very important twist that we're going to introduce.
So let's take a look. מאי שקדו. Mai shakdu. Where does this
idea come from that the rabbis wanted to make sure that you
got ready, that the groom got the wedding ready? דתניא, D'tanya, we've
taught in a ברייתא. braita. No, it just wants to know what's
the source. מפני מה אמרו בתולה נישאת ליום הרביעי? Mipnei ma amru
besula nises l'yom ha-revi'i? Why did they say that a virgin gets
married on Wednesday? שאם היה לו טענת בתולים היה משכים לבית דין,
She'im haya lo tanas besulim haya mashkim l'beis din, so he could
come to the court on the next day if the groom thought
that she wasn't a virgin. וכי תינשא באחד בשבת? V'chi tinesai b'echad
b'shabbos? How about Sunday? אם היה לו טענת בתולים היה משכים לבית
דין. Im haya lo tanas besulim haya mashkim l'beis din.
No. שקדו חכמים על תקנת בנות ישראל שיהא טורח בסעודה שלושה ימים.
Shakdu chachamim al takanas bnos Yisrael she-yehei torech b'seuda shlosha yamim. The
rabbis were conscientious about the, you know, to do something to protect
the interests, you know, or to establish an institution for the sake
of Jewish women that the groom should invest three days in getting
ready. אחד בשבת שני בשבת שלישי בשבת, Echad b'shabbos, sheni b'shabbos, shlishi
b'shabbos, Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, וברביעי כונסה, u'v'revi'i konesah, and on Wednesday marry.
Okay,
so that all we know, fine. Now it takes an interesting twist.
ומהסכנה ואילך, U'mei-hasakana v'eilach,
once there started being a danger involved in getting married on Wednesday,
נהגו לכנוס בשלישי, nahagu lichnos b'shlishi, they started getting married on Tuesday.
We're going to talk about it. ולא מיחו בידם חכמים ve'lo miku
beyadam chachamim and the rabbis didn't object. Okay. ובשני לא יכנס u'bishaini
lo yichanes
as a general rule don't get married on Tuesday, maybe even in
a case of danger or maybe we're not talking about a danger
case, a little debate over רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot how to
read that. Monday, what did I say? Okay. I'm sorry. In general
rule don't get married on Monday, okay, but ובשני לא יכנס u'bishaini
lo yichanes ואי מחמת האונס ve'i machmat ha'ones but if there was
some special circumstances, extenuating circumstances, מותר mutar you can get married on
Monday. So for סכנה sakana they got married on Tuesday, and if
there was a need, אונס ones which doesn't sound like סכנת נפשות
sakanat nefashot but some other extenuating circumstances you could even get married
on a Monday.
Okay. ומפרישין את החתן מן הכלה לילי שבת תחלה u'mafrishin et hachatan
min hakallah leilei shabbat techilah
and you separate חתן chatan and כלה kallah on Friday night, if
they haven't had sex yet, they make sure they don't have sex
on Friday night, מפני שהוא עושה חבורה mipnei shehu oseh chaburah because
the act of sex breaks ruptures the hymen and is like making
a wound on שבת. shabbat. So this is going to be a
big debate whether you can have sex for the first time on
Friday night, as I just told you in אשכנז Ashkenaz that's what
they would do all the time. Okay, we'll get to that later.
Not today. Today we're going to focus on this issue of סכנה
sakana and אונס. ones. What is the סכנה sakana that made them
do it on Tuesday? And what was the אונס ones that allowed
them to do it whatever day they needed to do it on,
Monday, but it doesn't seem דוקא davka Monday, it seems whatever day
you need to do it on. So let's take a look. מאי
סכנה, mai sakana, what was the danger? אילימא דאמרי בתולה נישאת ליום
רביעי תהרג, eileima de'amri betulah niseit leyom revii teihareig, let's say, you
know, classic סכנה, sakana, danger of life, is that the non-Jews want
to stamp out our religious practices. So what we're going to speculate
is, what would be the most direct connecting of the dots of
סכנה? sakana? They'd say, if you have this practice, this religious practice
of getting married on Wednesday, then you'll be put to death. Okay,
we're trying to they're trying to basically stamp out our religious practices,
so even though who really cares, Wednesday, what day,
whatever, but that's what the non-Jews said. Okay, so that's the סכנה,
sakana, direct סכנה sakana for doing this תקנה, takanah, for doing this
Wednesday. So that's true.
בתולה נישאת תהרג, betulah niseit teihareig, נהגו, nahagu, it says, oh, so
then the practice developed to go ahead the people would do it
on Tuesday. לעקריה לגמרי, le'akrei legamrei, why don't we just stop why
do we have to keep the תקנה takanah in place and let
people do it on Tuesday? If they said you're going to get
killed if you do it on Wednesday, we should say, you know
what guys, stop doing it on Wednesday, okay, why don't we completely
uproot it? Now of course by the way, there's a running question
that goes through this גמרא, Gemara, which is, if you uproot this
is what I'm going to say now applies to other things so
I'm not going to repeat it when we get to those other
scenarios. If you uprooted it and then you said don't do it
on Wednesday, do it on Tuesday, then they would just kill you
for doing it on Tuesday. Okay, but maybe it means we could
uproot it and say do it any day you want, so there's
no particular day that has religious significance. Okay, so why didn't we
just uproot it? Why did we just sort of keep it in
place but let people practice otherwise? So that's going to lead the
גמרא Gemara to interpret סכנה sakana differently. אמר רבא דאמרי, amar rava
de'amri, so they didn't say you'll get killed, but what they said
is בתולה נישאת ביום רביעי תיבעל להגמון תחלה, betulah niseit beyom revii
tiba-eil lehagmon techilah, when she gets married on Wednesday, she first has
sex with the like ruler of the city. Okay, this is what
was called what the droit de seigneur something, I mean this was
a real thing in the Middle Ages, right, that the whatever the
noble basically had the right to have sex with the brides on
the before the groom. So that's what they said. So therefore they
wanted to get out of that, so they figured we'll do it
on a different day, he won't realize we're getting married, he expects
us to get married on Wednesday. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
היי סכנה, hai sakana, so why are you calling it a danger
to life? אונס הוא, ones hu, it's a different thing, it's not
a danger to life, it's just that you're being forced to have
sex. It's rape, it's not a danger to life, it's different. So
describe the scenario differently. Why do you describe it as a danger?
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, משום דאיכא
צנועות דמסרן נפשייהו לקטלא, mishum de'ika tsnuot demasran nafshaihu lekatla, there's your
צנועות tsnuot again, because there are some people that rather than submit
would actually rather be killed. So for those people it is a
סכנה. sakana. Now the fact that it says צנועות tsnuot sounds like
they're operating more לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishurat hadin, not what the
legal requirement is. The legal
requirement is that they're allowed to submit and the גמרא Gemara is
going to say that explicitly. ואתיין לידי סכנה, ve'atyian lidei sakana, and
for those that want will resist it is going to be a
risk to life. So the גמרא Gemara says ולידרוש להו דאונס שרי,
ve'lidrosh lehu de'ones shari, but why are they risking
their lives? Why don't we just tell them, hey, you know, it's
okay, you're allowed to submit, you don't have to give up your
life for this? Now of course the question is, what do you
mean? Isn't גילוי עריות יהרג ואל יעבור? giluy arayot yeihareig ve'al ya'avor?
So this גמרא, Gemara, right, and she's already מקודשת, mekudeshet, right, so
this גמרא Gemara is very important in the יהרג ואל יעבור yeihareig
ve'al ya'avor story this discussion. This גמרא Gemara basically says that a
woman submits to an act of rape or unconsensual sex, even as
a married woman, and that she's allowed to do that rather than
giving up her life. Whatever happened to יהרג ואל יעבור? yeihareig ve'al
ya'avor? So there's a big תוספות Tosafot and Basically has two answers.
One answer is with a non-Jew it's different, okay, that sort of
sex with a non-Jew is seen categorically as different in terms of
the world of עריות arayos and is not גילוי עריות giluy arayos
and so on. Of course, the funny thing is like almost all
the cases that we imagine of being the יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg
ve'al ya'avor of גילוי עריות giluy arayos is sex with a non-Jew.
So תוספות Tosafos like really- this is a רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam
approach that תוספות Tosafos really rejects. But I want to say parenthetically
that רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam advanced this approach to deal with practical
cases, not forced sex, but a woman who basically converted
to Christianity, she was married, married a non-Jewish man, so halachically she's
having adultery. Then she came back to Judaism. The non-Jewish guy converted
to Judaism. And she was going to get a גט get from
her husband, would she be able to continue to live with this
non-Jewish guy or do we say אסורה לבעל אסורה לבועל, asura le'ba'al
asura le'boel, she's forbidden to the man that she had an affair
with? Okay, so רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam basically to deal with it-
I don't know how common this was, but to deal at least
with one case that presented itself like this, he basically said no,
sex with a non-Jew is completely in a different category of all
these things. It doesn't make her אסורה לבועל, asura le'boel, it's not
יהרג ואל יעבור. yehareg ve'al ya'avor. Okay, but anyway, that flies in
the face-
wait what did he do in the end?
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam allowed it but תוספות Tosafos doesn't like that.
Even with the second husband?
Yeah, I mean after she got a גט. get. Yes.
So תוספות Tosafos doesn't like that but that's one approach. The other
approach that generally is assumed to be the answer here is the
phrase that comes up in סנהדרין Sanhedrin about אישה קרקע עולם isha
karka olam or אסתר קרקע עולם, Esther karka olam, that if a
woman is somehow more passive then it's not יהרג ואל יעבור. yehareg
ve'al ya'avor. Now of course what does that mean? What does it
mean you conceive of a woman as completely passive in the act
of sex? She's never- she's just lying there flat not doing anything?
I mean,
so is that really how- what it's saying and therefore oh, if
it's passive there's no יהרג ואל יעבור? yehareg ve'al ya'avor? Example of
that תוספות Tosafos says is let's say somebody says I'm going to
throw you on a baby and use you to kill the baby.
Would you have to give up your life rather than doing it?
No, if you're completely passive then you don't have to give up
your life. You can't act on something. But is that really true
that we're saying that the woman doesn't do any act in the
act of sex? So it might be that's how הלכה halacha conceives
it, which would reflect a very particular type of like a male
bias and the man is the one doing the act of sex
and the woman is just the receptacle and so on. But another
explanation for this comes from the רמב"ן. Ramban. And the רמב"ן Ramban
basically said, he says rape is different because in rape even if
she would say kill me rather than rape me, the rapist could
rape her rather than kill her, right? The nature of the physical
nature of being overpowered and the anatomy of it is that she
doesn't really have a choice to give up her life rather than
commit the act, so therefore even if she agreed to commit the
act, we can't say she's sort of like choosing to do this
act because this act could be forced on her regardless. So that's
I think a much better explanation.
You mean even if the choice is presented to her, it's sort
of like a false choice.
Right, it's no real choice because she could say kill me and
he could say you know what, I'm going to rape you anyway.
Right. So therefore, so anyway, but this is an important גמרא. Gemara.
This גמרא Gemara seems to say that in this scenario, married woman,
non-Jew who says you've got to have sex with me first, that
it's not יהרג ואל יעבור. yehareg ve'al ya'avor. So the גמרא Gemara
therefore says so why is it סכנה? sakana? Right? You could say
it's an אונס, ones, but why are you calling it a סכנה?
sakana? Just because there are some women that think that they have
to give up their lives, why don't we tell them otherwise? So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers.
Why didn't we tell them then?
Because they- I understand but let's tell them, let's educate them. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, let me read it. No, משום
דאיכא דמיקטלא ואתיין לידי סכנה. mishum de'ika demikatla ve'asyan lidei sakana. ומידראש
דאונס שרי. ve'midrash de'ones shari. So
okay. Why do we tolerate that situation? If there are women giving
up their lives why are we tolerating it? Why don't we educate
them? No, איכא פרוצות ואיכא נמי כהנות. ika prutzos ve'ika nami kohanos.
No,
because educating them might be good that then they won't give up
their lives, but then there'll be scenarios if people learn like sometimes
a little knowledge is a dangerous thing, oh, if it's a סכנה
sakana it's okay, you're allowed to do it, then there're going to
be these cases when it's not a סכנה sakana and women who
are going to say well you know go ahead and do it
anyway, and oh it was a סכנה, sakana, they'll make the claim.
Now I don't know how often that פרוצות prutzos to that degree,
one thing פרוצות prutzos that you're too ready to assume your husband
is dead, another thing that you're submitting to this non-Jewish leader and
it's not really an אונס ones and you're claiming it's an אונס.
ones. Anyway, or the issue of כהנות kohanos is that even though
it is- כהנות kohanos we still have to deal with the consequence
that even though they're allowed to submit halachically, the consequence is still
that they're forbidden to their husbands כהנים. kohanim. So for them, they
might choose actually to like give up their lives because of the
irreversible sort of halachic consequence.
Does he mean the כהנות kohanos being married to a כהן? kohen?
כהנות kohanos means married to a כהן. kohen. Because of the irreversible
sort of halachic consequence. Now of course I don't- there's a very
complicated and difficult issue going on here, which is is the גמרא
Gemara saying why did we allow them to marry- to get married
on Tuesday? We should have told them to stay keep on getting
married on Wednesday to keep our תקנה, takana, and you've got a
problem that you've got to have sex with the guy, so have
sex with the guy! So it's allowed. Oh no, we can't say
that because even though it is allowed the wives of כהן... kohen...
Abraham, is that really what we're saying? That in order to keep
a תקנה takkanah of getting married on Wednesday, we'd prefer that they—since
technically it's allowed, we'd prefer for them to have sex, you know,
with this non-Jew? So it's better to read the גמרא—that's Gemara how
תוספות Tosafot reads the גמרא. Gemara. But that's like really deeply problematic.
So it's better to read the גמרא Gemara that the גמרא Gemara
is not questioning why, of course, they're going to start getting married
on Tuesday. The גמרא Gemara is only questioning why are we framing
it as סכנה sakanah rather than אונס? ones? Why didn't we educate
them enough so that it would have been an אונס ones scenario,
not a סכנה sakanah scenario? But of course, once you're dealing with
those circumstances, you've got to get out of them. You've got to
try to go ahead and get married on a different day. David,
you had a question?
Just since in
the
context that the נישואין nisuin had already occurred in terms of the
definition of adultery, right?
Yeah, so it's definitely adultery. Not only that, once קידושין kiddushin occurred—this
is only after the נישואין—but nisuin even after the קידושין, kiddushin, it's
adultery. Absolutely.
But even before the נישואין... nisuin...
No, it would still be adultery.
Sleeping with another man. Even without חופה, chuppah, once the קידושין kiddushin
occurred, once the ring was given over or the שקל shekel was
given over, whatever it was. Right.
Oh right, once that... but what would you... you said something about
a Jewish woman who then had sex with a non-Jewish man was
adultery... Yeah, that's in this context. That she's already in that process
of קידושין... kiddushin... she already did קידושין.
kiddushin. Okay. So let's see. So that's the... so the גמרא Gemara
says I still don't get why... so that's why it was an
אונס. ones. And that's why because of some reason, again, we decided
not to educate people. I mean, again, that's also shocking. You know,
you're not going to educate and save the lives of the צנועות
tzenuot because some people might misuse this information? But anyway, to some
degree, there was still some element of סכנה. sakanah. Even if we
would have educated people, there would still be those wives of כהנים,
Kohanim, there would still be cases of סכנה. sakanah. So we're calling
it סכנה. sakanah. To some degree, it really is an אונס, ones,
but we're going to call it סכנה. sakanah. And that's the reality.
And that's why they're getting married on a Tuesday and not on
a Wednesday to avoid having to submit to having sex with this
guy. So, you know, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, ולאעקרה, vela'akrei,
so, you know, so why don't we just say, okay, no longer
keep it on... don't just say we'll let them get married on
a different day, even if we want whatever, why don't we just
say no more any particular day to get married? Get married on
any day you want. Why do we keep the תקנה takkanah in
place? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, גזירה עבידה דבטלה. gezeira avidah
de-batlah. An edict of the government eventually will pass away. But תקנתא
דרבנן מקמי גזירה לא עקרינן. takkanata derabbanan mikamei gezeira lo akrinan. So
we're not going to change our legal system. You know, we've lived
through a lot of difficult times in history. We're not going to
go ahead and change our legal system every time there's a challenge
in history. We'll find a way to adapt, but we're not going
to change the basic system. That we want to sort of see
as more enduring. There's something very, I think, very inspiring about that.
Like, we have a long view. We're going to survive this. We'll
find a way to adapt now, we don't have to change the
הלכה, halacha, we'll adapt, we'll find a work-around, we're going to get
through this. Okay, so therefore we let people do it on a
Tuesday without actually changing the תקנה. takkanah. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אי הכי ee hachi בשלישי נמי אתי ובעיל? beshlishi nami atei u-va'iel?
But I don't get it. If they're starting to do it on
Tuesday, the guy will just show up to the town on Tuesdays.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, מספיקא לא עקר נפשיה. misfeka lo
akar nafshei. One, he doesn't know when's the wedding day. Once he
doesn't know what day they're getting married, right, he's not going to
show up to town every single day.
But maybe he really wants it if he's really that...
I understand, but it drastically will reduce the number of cases. When
there's no fixed day, when people could get married on any random
day, and how many weddings take place in a village in a
year, right? So, you know, so then it's a big ספק. safek.
So maybe sometimes, but it will drastically reduce it. Rather than if
he knows I'm going to go to every village on a Wednesday
in case there's a wedding. All right, so that's how we adapted
to that problem of avoiding that תקנה, takkanah, and that's why we've
kept the תקנה takkanah in place. But obviously, people started doing things
other than the תקנה takkanah to avoid having to deal with this.
Okay, so we will pick up with the remainder of this ברייתא
Baraita tomorrow. See you all
tonight,
right?
See you all tonight, or whoever's going to be there.